Aditya Naik

979-633-8551 | adityavnaik97@gmail.com | adityanaik.info | LinkedIn | GitHub

SUMMARY

AWS certified data engineer with 4+ years of experience in building and optimizing ETL data pipelines, data warehouses and data analytics systems using AWS, GCP, Spark, Flink, Kafka and PowerBI to drive business insights and decision-making.

EDUCATION

Texas A&M University - College Station, TX, USA

Master of Science in Management Information Systems

Pune University - Pune, India

Bachelor of Technology in Computer Engineering

September 2022 – May 2024

August 2015 – May 2019

SKILLS

Certifications: AWS Certified Developer, Professional Scrum Master

Languages: SQL, Python (Pandas, NumPy), Java, Scala, Bash, JavaScript, Groovy

Database: NoSQL (MongoDB, DynamoDB, Cassandra), Relational Databases (Postgres, MySQL, MSSQL)

Data: MapReduce, HDFS, Hadoop, HBase, Flume, Airflow, Kafka, SSIS, Snowflake, Dbt

BI Tools: Tableau, Power BI, Grafana, Looker, ClickHouse

Cloud: AWS (Redshift, EMR, Glue), GCP (BigQuery, DataFlow, Pub/Sub) **Other:** Git, JIRA, Jenkins, Terraform, Docker, Kubernetes, Agile, Scrum

EXPERIENCE

TAMU Institute of Technology Infused Learning

September 2022 – *May* 2024

Data Engineer - Spark, Hive, HDFS, Databricks, Python, Postgres, Tableau, Power BI, Data Warehouse, Excel

- Implemented Spark jobs for distributed data processing using Python Pyspark and SQL HiveQL in HDFS within Hadoop framework on Databricks, enhancing data cleaning and data integration efficiency by 5x.
- Designed ETL workflows in Spark via DAGs, and integrated 120 GB of customer demographics, transactions and sales revenue data from 50 different Excel sources in PostgreSQL.
- Established data warehouse and data marts in Star and Snowflake schema via dimensional data modeling for MPP databases.
- Crafted Tableau dashboards to visualize effects of marketing campaigns on sales, empowering decision-making and reducing analysis time by 10x.

HSBC Holdings PLC October 2020 – July 2022

Data Engineer II - SQL, ETL, ELT, Kafka, Flink, AWS, S3, Redshift, Airflow, Data Pipeline, Data Lake, DBT, EMR

- Optimized complex SQL queries and performance tuning through indexes, partitions, stored procedures, triggers and aggregations, resulting in faster generation of financial reports for stakeholders by 59%.
- Constructed scalable ETL /ELT data pipelines using Airflow and Apache Flink in EMR for data processing to migrate legacy order management system (Fidessa) to AWS, saving \$40,000/year in license and operational costs.
- Implemented Kafka consumers for data ingestion and real-time streaming of financial transaction events of petabyte scale from topics through RESTful APIs, reducing asynchronous stream and batch processing latency by 65%.
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams of analysts, creating big data architecture through data models and NoSQL schemas for data warehouse Redshift and data lakes to support 15 analytical reporting systems.
- Utilized SQL for ad-hoc data analysis and reporting, providing actionable insights to stakeholders and supporting financial processes for Equities, Derivatives and Fixed Income products, ensuring data consistency and reliability across systems.

HSBC Technology

July 2019 – October 2020

Software Engineer - Java, CI/CD, Jenkins, Docker, Kubernetes, Unix, Bash, Git

- Built Jenkins CI/CD pipelines and used Kubernetes for orchestrating Docker containers, elevating release frequency by 5x.
- $\bullet \ \ Automated \ Linux \ virtual \ machines \ provision \ in \ GCP \ via \ shell \ scripts, \ reducing \ manual \ intervention \ to \ 0\% \ in \ production \ servers.$
- Coordinated Scrum ceremonies in Agile teams using JIRA and provided code documentation via version control tools.

PROJECTS

Online QnA forum using AWS | GitHub

- Created data storage in DynamoDB, S3 and caching in Redis for 90 GB of unstructured data of students and questions.
- Architected ETL data pipelines using AWS Glue, to extract questions, aggregate student marks and load into Redshift.
- Designed microservices as AWS Lambda functions in Python and deployed via Terraform reducing deployment time by 45%.

Gen AI model for disease classification (Hackathon Winner) | Link

- Generated synthetic healthcare datasets for preliminary disease using NLP and TensorFlow.
- Performed predictive analytics using Gen AI on historical database of physician comments with 98% accuracy